<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>λ Tony's blog λ — Posts tagged KTM</title>
    <link href="http://blog.tmorris.net/tags/KTM.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="http://blog.tmorris.net" />
    <id>http://blog.tmorris.net/tags/KTM.xml</id>
    <author>
        <name>Tony Morris</name>
        <email>blog@tmorris.net</email>
    </author>
    <updated>2015-05-24T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <entry>
    <title>24 May 2015 Thulimbah Ride Report</title>
    <link href="http://blog.tmorris.net/posts/thulimbah-ride-report/index.html" />
    <id>http://blog.tmorris.net/posts/thulimbah-ride-report/index.html</id>
    <published>2015-05-24T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-05-24T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="ride-20150524-thulimbah">Ride 20150524 Thulimbah</h1>
<p>We planned to meet at Rathdowney around 0845 on the Sunday morning, knowing that Rob &amp; Athol had never seen the granite belt. We would take Mt Lindesay Highway (or is it Road? haha, there is a back-story to that) to Woodenbong then Legume, before stopping at the <a href="http://www.openstreetmap.org/?mlat=-28.4351&amp;mlon=152.3838#map=15/-28.4351/152.3838">Maryland River Bridge</a> for some beach riding. Soon, we’d turn on to the scenic <a href="http://www.openstreetmap.org/?mlat=-28.5496&amp;mlon=152.1307#map=15/-28.5496/152.1307">Wylie Creek Road</a> through <a href="http://www.openstreetmap.org/?mlat=-28.5627&amp;mlon=151.9986#map=14/-28.5627/151.9986">Maryland</a> and on to Thulimbah.</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/1O8JLGQZtBY" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen>
</iframe>
<hr />
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/LYD-fTzxMRM" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen>
</iframe>
<hr />
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/UmRwWG7.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/UmRwWG7.jpg" alt="" style="width: 640px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<p>Not another body in sight, only moo-cows, we started the slow climb from 500 to 950 metres above sea level. Arriving at Thulimbah, we did a loop of the Hinze Enduro Loop, then said our goodbyes.</p>
<p>Entering <a href="http://www.openstreetmap.org/#map=13/-28.5642/151.8168">Passchendaele State Forest</a> from the east, we did a few little loops before deciding that food and fuel were in order. Having already seen an abundance of wildlife, I was mindful of the risks at highway speed. That was when a tidings of magpies took off from the shoulder of the road. Having no air traffic control in this area, these magpies were completely unaware of my ground speed, which tripled their take-off speed. One of the individuals, mistakenly, chose the strategy of “outpace the threat.” There was no way to save it, and before I could let up the brakes, I could see an explosion of feathers in the mirror. I ventured back to make sure there was no more suffering and despite the unfortunate circumstance, felt a mild relief that it was all over for that miscalculating magpie.</p>
<p>We fueled and ate at Stanthorpe, while planning the next leg. Another journey into Passchendaele was all too tempting. Aiming for <a href="http://www.openstreetmap.org/?mlat=-28.60556&amp;mlon=151.78448#map=17/-28.60556/151.78448">Swiper’s Gully</a>, and not knowing if the rabbit fence would prevent access, I came upon some familiar track landmarks where I reassured myself that this was the way in.</p>
<p>That was when we decided to stop for a short meeting and Rob’s DRZ became a DRZZZZZZ. Refusing to rest on the kickstand, the DRZ chose to have a little snooze on its left side. Once again <a href="http://tonymorris.github.io/blog/posts/mount-mee-ride-report/index.html">[last time]</a>, we broke out the orange toolkit for adjustments and repairs. Soon, we were on the trail to Swiper’s Gully at the south end of Passchendaele. Hooting through the rocky, thin trails, a wild pig scooted out of our way, and then we came upon an emu carcass. Black cockatoos called out as an eagle left its high perch in a tree. That was when I knew, dusk was coming.</p>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/jdTc4WY.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/jdTc4WY.jpg" alt="" style="width: 640px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/K0jVATR.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/K0jVATR.jpg" alt="" style="width: 640px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<p>Turning the bikes east along Donnellys Castle Road, the abundance of bouncing wallabies, while serene, also served as a caution of what was ahead. Thulimbah, then Wylie Creek Road, I must have seen 40 wallabies by now. We stopped for a road-side meeting where we discussed the dangers ahead. As the sun went down, I saw a small kangaroo leap in front of Rob’s bike. Close call, I thought, but then a larger roo followed behind, looking to take on the idling DRZ at 70kph. It was one of those moments where there is no time to reach for the brake; just a shot of adrenaline as the big lumbering beast appears in the headlight beam and before there is any reaction, it is all over. It must have missed Rob’s DR-Z by less than a metre, from where I was, about 40 metres behind.</p>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/bITOXQZ.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/bITOXQZ.jpg" alt="" style="width: 640px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/wtlkoix.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/wtlkoix.jpg" alt="" style="width: 640px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/0z9rLiS.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/0z9rLiS.jpg" alt="" style="width: 640px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/9nzbTIR.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/9nzbTIR.jpg" alt="" style="width: 640px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<p>We stopped again at the end of Wylie Creek Road for a meeting. By now, the sun was truly gone and Venus and Jupiter were shining bright in the northern sky. Athol asked, “where is Rathdowney from here?” Why, it’s just over the hill yonder, a tad beyond Legume, a smaller tad passed Woodenbong and then a tiny tad and we are there!</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/24nHE-tflII" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen>
</iframe>
<hr />
<p>We had another couple of hours ahead of us and Athol was regretting having a dependence on the factory headlight. Never again, I swore, after doing the same journey with a Husqvarna factory headlight years ago. Corners are like the lottery; maybe there is an obstacle in two seconds time, but you won’t know it until it’s too late. The cold was setting in and I turned on the heated grips.</p>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/jbScRQW.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/jbScRQW.jpg" alt="" style="width: 640px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<p>We held a steady pace for the next hour or so, to Woodenbong for the next meeting. By now, shivering was the only remaining strategy against the wind chill. Not long to go now. Rathdowney wasn’t too far away, and only another 110km after that and I’d be home.</p>
<p>Winding through the twisty roads of Mount Lindesay Highway, using the advisory speed signs to estimate corner entrance speed, we came upon a plonker. This was the type of plonker who would enter a corner far too slow, speed up mid-corner, overshoot, then use the brakes to adjust. Yeah those plonkers, and not a straight-away for a long time.</p>
<p>Fifteen minutes of cornering like a see-saw with bipolar disorder, finally, the solid white line gave way and it was throttles wound on. Rob and Athol didn’t make it, but I got up to the posted speed limit and set in for the final leg to Rathdowney. Arriving there in short order, I parked up the KTM next to the parked car and waited. I could hear the two DRZs puttering along, approaching.</p>
<p>That was when … the unbelievable happened. My eyes were deceiving me. It just wasn’t happening. Was this real? Did I just see that? Did I miss a memo? Is there something I have simply misunderstood? These questions raced through my mind as the two DRZs could be heard in the distance, fading away. They’d both ridden to Rathdowney, along the main stretch of road, then <strong>kept going</strong>.</p>
<p>I could not figure out how this plan change could have worked out. By what method had these two come to the conclusion that passing through Rathdowney was going to work? It was now 2100 in the evening. That would mean the car must stay here, in Rathdowney. Just what was the plan?</p>
<p>Then it hit me. There was no plan. My friends, as adorable as they are, have completely missed the fact that they’d passed through Rathdowney. In their mind, Rathdowney was perpetually in front of them. It was time to act quick. Soon, they’d be out of phone range. I got through to Athol first, insisting that he’d ridden straight through Rathdowney. Then the phone cut out.</p>
<p>I rang Rob, “You’ve ridden through Rathdowney. Turn around and come back!” He didn’t believe me. OK, fine, two DRZs just went through Rathdowney; one with exactly the same spotlight configuration as Rob’s bike and another with a factory headlight, but it was someone else.</p>
<p>I later learned that Rob and Athol had a roadside meeting, where there was scepticism that they’d passed through Rathdowney, but decided to turn around anyway, just to confirm my mistake.</p>
<p>I set up a strobe light for their impending return, so as not to lose them again and sure enough, 10 minutes later, the approaching single cylinders could be heard in the distance. I was in awe. I am still in awe.</p>
<hr />
<h3 id="bikes">Bikes</h3>
<ul>
<li><p>2014 KTM 690 Enduro R, <strong>Tony</strong></p></li>
<li><p>2011 Suzuki DR-Z400, <strong>Athol</strong></p></li>
<li><p>2013 Suzuki DR-Z400, <strong>Rob</strong></p></li>
</ul>
<hr />
<h3 id="track-log">Track log</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://latlon.org/show_gpx?gpx_url=https%3A%2F%2Fraw.githubusercontent.com%2Ftonymorris%2Fgpx%2Fmaster%2Ftrk%2F20150524-ride-stanthorpe.gpx">Map</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/tonymorris/gpx/master/trk/20150524-ride-stanthorpe.gpx">Raw GPX</a></p></li>
</ul>
<iframe width="800" height="600" src="http://latlon.org/show_gpx?gpx_url=https%3A%2F%2Fraw.githubusercontent.com%2Ftonymorris%2Fgpx%2Fmaster%2Ftrk%2F20150524-ride-stanthorpe.gpx" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen>
</iframe>
<hr />
<p><a href="https://i.imgur.com/UCipKNO.png"><img src="https://i.imgur.com/UCipKNO.png" alt="" style="width: 640px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<p><a href="https://i.imgur.com/9NNAwP1.png"><img src="https://i.imgur.com/9NNAwP1.png" alt="" style="width: 640px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<p><a href="https://i.imgur.com/lMEl4cm.png"><img src="https://i.imgur.com/lMEl4cm.png" alt="" style="width: 640px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<h3 id="route">Route</h3>
<ul>
<li>Rathdowney</li>
<li>Woodenbong</li>
<li>Legume</li>
<li>Maryland</li>
<li>Thulimbah</li>
<li>Donnellys Castle</li>
<li>Passchendaele State Forest</li>
<li>Stanthorpe</li>
<li>Passchendaele State Forest</li>
<li>Thulimbah</li>
<li>Maryland</li>
<li>Legume</li>
<li>Woodenbong</li>
<li>Rathdowney</li>
<li>A little bit past Rathdowney because, well, some of us are not navigationally literate</li>
</ul>
<hr />
<h3 id="statistics">Statistics</h3>
<h5 id="elevation-over-distance">Elevation over distance</h5>
<p><a href="https://i.imgur.com/YsKo0KC.png"><img src="https://i.imgur.com/YsKo0KC.png" alt="" style="width: 640px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<h5 id="elevation-over-time">Elevation over time</h5>
<p><a href="https://i.imgur.com/9DDjZ2I.png"><img src="https://i.imgur.com/9DDjZ2I.png" alt="" style="width: 640px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<h5 id="distance-over-time">Distance over time</h5>
<p><a href="https://i.imgur.com/PTHdq2g.png"><img src="https://i.imgur.com/PTHdq2g.png" alt="" style="width: 640px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<ul>
<li><strong>Minimum elevation</strong>: 91m asl</li>
<li><strong>Maximum elevation</strong>: 970m asl</li>
<li><strong>Average elevation</strong>: 624.2m asl</li>
<li><strong>Maximum difference</strong>: 879m</li>
<li><strong>Total climbing</strong>: 7795m</li>
<li><strong>Total descent</strong>: 7801m</li>
<li><strong>Start elevation</strong>: 102m asl</li>
<li><strong>End elevation</strong>: 96m asl</li>
<li><strong>Final balance</strong>: -6m</li>
</ul>
<hr />
<ul>
<li><strong>Minimum speed</strong>: 0.9kph</li>
<li><strong>Maximum speed</strong>: 192.4kph</li>
<li><strong>Average climbing speed</strong>: 72.5kph</li>
<li><strong>Average descent speed</strong>: 70.8kph</li>
<li><strong>Average flat speed</strong>: 67.6kph</li>
<li><strong>Average speed</strong>: 70.1kph</li>
</ul>
<hr />
<ul>
<li><strong>Total track time</strong>: 11h 58m 05s</li>
<li><strong>Climbing time</strong>: 3h 30m 25s</li>
<li><strong>Descent time</strong>: 5h 57m 12s</li>
<li><strong>Flat time</strong>: 2h 30m 28s</li>
</ul>
<hr />
<ul>
<li><strong>Total flat distance</strong>: 377.4km</li>
<li><strong>Total real distance</strong>: 378.4km</li>
<li><strong>Climbing distance</strong>: 123.5km</li>
<li><strong>Descent distance</strong>: 121.1km</li>
<li><strong>Flat distance</strong>: 133.8km</li>
</ul>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>09 May 2015 Mount Mee Ride Report</title>
    <link href="http://blog.tmorris.net/posts/mount-mee-ride-report/index.html" />
    <id>http://blog.tmorris.net/posts/mount-mee-ride-report/index.html</id>
    <published>2015-05-24T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-05-24T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="ride-20150509-mount-mee">Ride 20150509 Mount Mee</h1>
<p>We left Everton Hills, bound for Dayboro, the unmissable town before Mount Mee. Rob D. had a small dingle on a narrow, downhill bend, leading into a single-lane bridge. He had a couple of scratches and so did the KLR, but soon we were back on the road.</p>
<p>At Dayboro, we grabbed a drink before heading up the hill. Soon we were on the gravel fire trails of Mount Mee State Forest and the tiny 17&quot; supermoto front wheel (with a Pirelli Corsa Rosso tyre) of the 690 constantly demanded fast reflexes.</p>
<p>Headed up to Wivenhoe Lookout, the fun way, with the jumps, then on to Rocky Hole. When we arrived at Woodford, Rob D. had had enough of the loose surface and took the tar road. Rob H. and I turned back the way we came and nailed it through the forest.</p>
<p>Soon, we were back on the tar, heading home. That was when I was hit in the <strong>helmet visor</strong> by a loose bolt from the leading DR-Z at 100kph. After my initial shock of this profound collision, I looked up to see the rear guard of the DR-Z thrashing around loosely. Nothing some cable-ties couldn’t fix.</p>
<p>When we arrived at base, we parked up the KTM, DR-Z and KLR. As thoughts of having a post-ride beer came upon us, instead, we were obliged to repair the lesser two of the three. The DR-Z needed a less temporary repair for its missing bolt and the KLR had lost its seat mount bolts and one <strong>rear subframe bolt</strong>. The KTM watched on.</p>
<p>Now to be completely fair, all was not free for the KTM. It too required repairs. Given its nature, it had devoured a rear tyre (again, Pirelli Corsa Rosso).</p>
<p>Once the KLR and DR-Z were put back together, with assistance from the All Hours Everton Hills Bolt &amp; Tool Shop, they were on the way.</p>
<p>The KTM will be fed its usual diet of rubber through the week.</p>
<hr />
<h3 id="bikes">Bikes</h3>
<ul>
<li><p>2014 KTM 690 Enduro R</p></li>
<li><p>2013 Kawasaki KLR 650</p></li>
<li><p>2013 Suzuki DR-Z400</p></li>
</ul>
<hr />
<h3 id="track-log">Track log</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://latlon.org/show_gpx?gpx_url=https://raw.githubusercontent.com/tonymorris/gpx/master/trk/20150509-ride-mountmee.gpx">Map</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/tonymorris/gpx/master/trk/20150509-ride-mountmee.gpx">Raw GPX</a></p></li>
</ul>
<p><a href="https://i.imgur.com/Y8GtKPj.png"><img src="https://i.imgur.com/Y8GtKPj.png" alt="" style="width: 660px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<h3 id="route">Route</h3>
<ul>
<li><p>Everton Hills</p></li>
<li><p>Dayboro</p></li>
<li><p>Mount Mee (The Gantry)</p></li>
<li><p>Mount Mee (Wivenhoe Lookout)</p></li>
<li><p>Mount Mee (Rocky Hole)</p></li>
<li><p>Woodford</p></li>
<li><p>Mount Mee (The Gantry)</p></li>
<li><p>Dayboro</p></li>
<li><p>Everton Hills</p></li>
</ul>
<hr />
<h3 id="statistics">Statistics</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Minimum elevation:</strong> -85 m.s.l.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Maximum elevation:</strong> 649 m.s.l.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Average elevation:</strong> 237.2 m.s.l.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Total climbing:</strong> 4142 m</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Total descent:</strong> 4414 m</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Start elevation:</strong> 360.2 m.s.l.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>End elevation:</strong> 88 m.s.l.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Final balance:</strong> -272.2 m</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Minimum speed:</strong> 3.2 km/h</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Maximum speed:</strong> 192 km/h</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Average climbing speed:</strong> 58.5 km/h</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Average descent speed:</strong> 54.9 km/h</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Average flat speed:</strong> 59.4 km/h</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Average speed:</strong> 57.4 km/h</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Climbing time:</strong> 2h 35m 45s</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Descent time:</strong> 1h 40m 33s</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Total track time:</strong> 5h 04m 15s</p></li>
</ul>
<hr />
<h5 id="elevation-over-distance">Elevation over distance</h5>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/urKRq6V.png"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/urKRq6V.png" alt="" style="width: 660px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<h5 id="elevation-over-time">Elevation over time</h5>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/ZMOZFdh.png"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/ZMOZFdh.png" alt="" style="width: 660px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<h3 id="photos">Photos</h3>
<h5 id="after-the-klr-broke-i-wisely-use-the-ktm-toolkit-to-fix-it.">After the KLR broke, I wisely use the KTM toolkit to fix it.</h5>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/DFtERs0.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/DFtERs0.jpg" alt="" style="width: 660px;"/></a></p>
<!--

<a href="http://i.imgur.com/M66T6xt.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/M66T6xt.jpg" alt="" style="width: 660px;"/></a>

<a href="http://i.imgur.com/Jay4gfY.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/Jay4gfY.jpg" alt="" style="width: 660px;"/></a>

<a href="http://i.imgur.com/rewEpZy.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/rewEpZy.jpg" alt="" style="width: 660px;"/></a>

<a href="http://i.imgur.com/kyGuDZ7.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/kyGuDZ7.jpg" alt="" style="width: 660px;"/></a>

-->
<hr />
<h5 id="wivenhoe-lookout-mount-mee">Wivenhoe Lookout, Mount Mee</h5>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/mEQD4zy.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/mEQD4zy.jpg" alt="" style="width: 660px;"/></a></p>
<!--

<a href="http://i.imgur.com/KqIC8a5.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/KqIC8a5.jpg" alt="" style="width: 660px;"/></a>

-->
<!--

<a href="http://i.imgur.com/KnnBQ39.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/KnnBQ39.jpg" alt="" style="width: 660px;"/></a>

-->
<hr />
<h5 id="when-we-got-back-home-the-ktm-parked-up-but-the-klr-and-dr-z-needed-repairs">When we got back home, the KTM parked up, but the KLR and DR-Z needed repairs…</h5>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/8KfgOXJ.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/8KfgOXJ.jpg" alt="" style="width: 660px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<h5 id="and-more-repairs">…and more repairs…</h5>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/PIWttH5.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/PIWttH5.jpg" alt="" style="width: 660px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<h5 id="using-the-appropriate-toolkit.">…using the appropriate toolkit.</h5>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/3tEoyjK.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/3tEoyjK.jpg" alt="" style="width: 660px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<h5 id="bolts-had-been-left-back-at-mount-mee.-if-you-look-closely-in-the-background-you-can-see-a-ktm-parked-waiting-watching-yearning-for-the-next-blat.">Bolts had been left back at Mount Mee. If you look closely in the background, you can see a KTM parked, waiting, watching, yearning for the next blat.</h5>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/ExbXsCD.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/ExbXsCD.jpg" alt="" style="width: 660px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<h5 id="here-is-a-dr-z-rider-looking-for-a-missing-bolt.-i-dont-like-his-chances.">Here is a DR-Z rider, looking for a missing bolt. I don’t like his chances.</h5>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/tUJffDD.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/tUJffDD.jpg" alt="" style="width: 660px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<h5 id="i-like-drinking-beer-while-watching.-the-ktm-is-ready-for-the-next-ride.">I like drinking beer while watching. The KTM is ready for the next ride.</h5>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/D06HKcJ.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/D06HKcJ.jpg" alt="" style="width: 660px;"/></a></p>
<hr />]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>19 April 2015 Brisbane/Thulimbah return Ride Report</title>
    <link href="http://blog.tmorris.net/posts/brisbane-thulimbah-return-ride-report/index.html" />
    <id>http://blog.tmorris.net/posts/brisbane-thulimbah-return-ride-report/index.html</id>
    <published>2015-05-24T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-05-24T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="bike">Bike</h1>
<ul>
<li>2014 KTM 690 Enduro R (supermoto modified. <a href="http://tonymorris.github.io/blog/posts/ktm690-enduro-smc/index.html">Here is a post</a> on the modification.)</li>
</ul>
<hr />
<h1 id="track">Track</h1>
<h3 id="track-log">Track log</h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://bit.ly/1yGiA4P" class="uri">http://bit.ly/1yGiA4P</a></li>
</ul>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/KCtUuXX.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/KCtUuXX.jpg" alt="track log" style="width: 678px;"/></a></p>
<h3 id="stats">Stats</h3>
<ul>
<li>Total distance: 619.49km</li>
<li>Minimum altitude: 10m asl</li>
<li>Maximum altitude: 938m asl</li>
<li>Climb: 12402m</li>
<li>Descent: 12412m</li>
<li>Track profile</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/ZYqCy3l.png"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/ZYqCy3l.png" alt="track profile" style="width: 678px;"/></a></p>
<h3 id="route">Route</h3>
<ul>
<li>Brisbane</li>
<li>Beaudesert</li>
<li>Rathdowney</li>
<li>Woodenbong</li>
<li>Legume</li>
<li>Maryland</li>
<li>The Summit</li>
<li>Thulimbah</li>
<li>Maryland</li>
<li>Legume</li>
<li>Woodenbong</li>
<li>Rathdowney</li>
<li>Tamrookum</li>
<li>Hillview</li>
<li>Duck Creek Road</li>
<li>Lamington National Park</li>
<li>Canungra</li>
<li>Yarrabilba</li>
<li>Rochedale</li>
<li>Brisbane</li>
</ul>
<hr />
<h1 id="photos-chronological-order">Photos <em>(chronological order)</em></h1>
<h5 id="yowies-here-mt-lindesay-highway-between-rathdowney-and-woodenbong">“Yowies Here”, Mt Lindesay Highway, between Rathdowney and Woodenbong</h5>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/1k2zOc8.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/1k2zOc8.jpg" alt="Yowies Here" style="width: 672px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<h5 id="yowies-here-mt-lindesay-highway-between-rathdowney-and-woodenbong-1">“Yowies Here”, Mt Lindesay Highway, between Rathdowney and Woodenbong</h5>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/L5kzxi3.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/L5kzxi3.jpg" alt="Yowies Here" style="width: 672px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<h5 id="yowies-here-mt-lindesay-highway-between-rathdowney-and-woodenbong-2">“Yowies Here”, Mt Lindesay Highway, between Rathdowney and Woodenbong</h5>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/blJbOVC.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/blJbOVC.jpg" alt="Yowies Here" style="width: 672px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<h5 id="maryland-river-from-the-bridge">Maryland River from the bridge</h5>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/UKjTgy0.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/UKjTgy0.jpg" alt="Maryland River" style="width: 672px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<h5 id="wylie-creek-road-maryland">Wylie Creek Road, Maryland</h5>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/ODwKlAq.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/ODwKlAq.jpg" alt="Wylie Creek Road" style="width: 672px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<h5 id="wylie-creek-road-maryland-early-morning">Wylie Creek Road, Maryland <em>(early morning)</em></h5>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/xMknDqR.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/xMknDqR.jpg" alt="Wylie Creek Road" style="width: 672px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<h5 id="wylie-creek-road-maryland-early-morning-1">Wylie Creek Road, Maryland <em>(early morning)</em></h5>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/V4qpOmd.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/V4qpOmd.jpg" alt="Wylie Creek Road" style="width: 672px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<h5 id="wylie-creek-road-maryland-early-morning-2">Wylie Creek Road, Maryland <em>(early morning)</em></h5>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/JeAo4J9.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/JeAo4J9.jpg" alt="Wylie Creek Road" style="width: 672px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<h5 id="wylie-creek-road-maryland-early-morning-3">Wylie Creek Road, Maryland <em>(early morning)</em></h5>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/VjaWzbP.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/VjaWzbP.jpg" alt="Wylie Creek Road" style="width: 672px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<h5 id="wylie-creek-road-maryland-early-morning-4">Wylie Creek Road, Maryland <em>(early morning)</em></h5>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/xWpeGIe.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/xWpeGIe.jpg" alt="Wylie Creek Road" style="width: 672px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<h5 id="wylie-creek-road-turnoff-maryland-early-morning">Wylie Creek Road (turnoff), Maryland <em>(early morning)</em></h5>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/F8A42J7.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/F8A42J7.jpg" alt="Wylie Creek Road" style="width: 672px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<h5 id="turtle-on-wylie-creek-road">Turtle on Wylie Creek Road</h5>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/LbwtZtI.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/LbwtZtI.jpg" alt="Turtle on Wylie Creek Road" style="width: 672px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<h5 id="turtle-on-wylie-creek-road-1">Turtle on Wylie Creek Road</h5>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/BzFYKaH.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/BzFYKaH.jpg" alt="Turtle on Wylie Creek Road" style="width: 672px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<h5 id="turtle-on-wylie-creek-road-2">Turtle on Wylie Creek Road</h5>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/IpyrQi0.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/IpyrQi0.jpg" alt="Turtle on Wylie Creek Road" style="width: 672px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<h5 id="maryland-river-bridge-httpbit.ly1osj3oj">Maryland River Bridge <em><a href="http://bit.ly/1OsJ3oj" class="uri">http://bit.ly/1OsJ3oj</a></em></h5>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/rQozDCy.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/rQozDCy.jpg" alt="Maryland River Bridge" style="width: 672px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<h5 id="maryland-river-bridge-httpbit.ly1osj3oj-1">Maryland River Bridge <em><a href="http://bit.ly/1OsJ3oj" class="uri">http://bit.ly/1OsJ3oj</a></em></h5>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/5i6wyl1.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/5i6wyl1.jpg" alt="Maryland River Bridge" style="width: 672px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<h5 id="maryland-river-bridge-httpbit.ly1osj3oj-2">Maryland River Bridge <em><a href="http://bit.ly/1OsJ3oj" class="uri">http://bit.ly/1OsJ3oj</a></em></h5>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/7LZmdej.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/7LZmdej.jpg" alt="Maryland River Bridge" style="width: 672px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<h5 id="maryland-river-bridge-httpbit.ly1osj3oj-3">Maryland River Bridge <em><a href="http://bit.ly/1OsJ3oj" class="uri">http://bit.ly/1OsJ3oj</a></em></h5>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/K7gN56B.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/K7gN56B.jpg" alt="Maryland River Bridge" style="width: 672px;"/></a></p>
<hr />]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>2014 KTM 690 Enduro to Supermoto</title>
    <link href="http://blog.tmorris.net/posts/ktm690-enduro-smc/index.html" />
    <id>http://blog.tmorris.net/posts/ktm690-enduro-smc/index.html</id>
    <published>2015-01-07T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-01-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This article is a description of the conversion of a 2014 KTM 690 Enduro R to a Supermoto with 17&quot; wheels. Two goals are kept in mind:</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li><p>It is easy to go back to Enduro configuration.</p></li>
<li><p>It is easy to go back to factory. This refers to minimising the irreversible modification of factory parts.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>Part names and numbers will be provided.</p>
<p>If you would like me to do this conversion for on your bike and you are able to transport your motorcycle to Brisbane, please email me and I will be happy to help you.</p>
<p><a href="tonymorris@gmail.com" class="uri">tonymorris@gmail.com</a></p>
<h3 id="motorcycle-models">Motorcycle models</h3>
<p>The motorcycle was already heavily modified (details below). It is an Australian version of the KTM 690 Enduro R, which closely resembles the EU version. I would expect that the modification described here would apply, without alteration, to US models.</p>
<p>I also expect that this description would apply to earlier year models, with exception for taking into account the ABS. The use of ABS in the 2014 model only changes the following facts:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>There is no need to purchase the ABS sensor rings for the supermoto wheels.</p></li>
<li><p>The earlier models use different wheel bushing/spacer widths, which:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>are supplied with the supermoto wheels for all year models</p></li>
<li><p>required customisation for the rear wheel in my case anyway</p></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<h3 id="wheels">Wheels</h3>
<p>In August 2014, I purchased the front wheel, rear wheel and cush-drive hub with 44T sprocket from <a href="http://www.warp9racing.com/sm_wheels_KTM.html">warp9racing.com</a>:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>ASSEMBLED KTM 690 FRONT WHEEL - 17“X3.50” BLACK HUB / BLACK RIM / SILVER SPOKES WITH SILVER NIPPLES INCLUDES 300MM FLOATING ROTOR WITH SPACERS</p>
<p><code>USD468.00</code></p></li>
<li><p>ASSEMBLED KTM 690 ENDURO REAR WHEEL - 17“X4.25” ORANGE HUB / BLACK RIM / SILVER SPOKES WITH SILVER NIPPLES INCLUDES ROTOR</p>
<p><code>USD468.00</code></p></li>
<li><p>KTM 690 CUSH DRIVE WITH SPROCKET (USES OEM RUBBERS) 44T</p>
<p><code>USD139.00</code></p></li>
</ul>
<hr />
<p>When the wheels arrived, they looked like this:</p>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/rmurQaG.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/rmurQaG.jpg" alt="warp9racing supermoto wheels" style="width: 1032px;"/></a></p>
<p>Note that the wheels included:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>disc brakes</p></li>
<li><p>wheel bushings/spacers</p></li>
</ul>
<h3 id="abs-sensor-rings">ABS Sensor Rings</h3>
<p>I chose to buy a second set of ABS sensor rings and factory bolts to use on the supermoto wheels, so that I didn’t have to remove them whenever I wanted to go back to Enduro configuration.</p>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>1x</strong> SENSOR WHEEL FRONT (KTM part <code>60142020000</code>)</p>
<p><code>USD23.46</code></p></li>
<li><p><strong>1x</strong> SENSOR WHEEL ABS REAR (KTM part <code>76542021000</code>)</p>
<p><code>USD23.36</code></p></li>
<li><p><strong>15x</strong> ZYL.SCHRAUBE DIN14580 M6X16 (KTM part <code>014580060166S</code>)</p>
<p><code>USD11.25</code> (<code>USD0.79</code> each)</p></li>
</ul>
<hr />
<p>Each ABS sensor requires six (6) of the Zylinderkopf DIN14580 Torx bolts. I purchased a total of fifteen (15) so that I had 3 spares.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://github.com/tonymorris/ktm690/blob/master/manuals.md">KTM 690 service manual</a><a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"><sup>1</sup></a> specifies the following for these bolts:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Tighten to 14Nm (10.3 lbf·ft) torque</p></li>
<li><p>Use Loctite 243 (thread locker)</p></li>
<li><p>“The lettering on the ABS sensor wheel is located on the outside.”</p></li>
</ul>
<hr />
<p>After fitment of the ABS sensor rings, the wheels now look like this:</p>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/oP0tzZI.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/oP0tzZI.jpg" alt="warp9racing supermoto wheels, with ABS sensor" style="width: 1032px;"/></a></p>
<h1 id="tyres">Tyres</h1>
<p>I fitted Pirelli Diablo Rosso tyres to the rims. The tyre sizes were chosen for their application, however, it was later learned that the size is also important for fitment. Specifically, the front tyre is at the limit of maximum width without fouling.</p>
<p>I also used tubes and rim bands.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Front <code>150/60-ZR17</code></p></li>
<li><p>Rear <code>120/70-ZR17</code></p></li>
</ul>
<h1 id="rear-wheel-fitment">Rear Wheel Fitment</h1>
<p>Using the warp9racing supplied bushings, I was able to fit the rear wheel, however, it was clearly malaligned, since:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>the inside brake pad friction was preventing wheel rotation</p></li>
<li><p>the ABS sensor ring bolt heads fouled the rear brake caliper</p>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/zaIwNkG.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/zaIwNkG.jpg" alt="warp9racing supermoto rear wheel, malaligned" style="height: 1033px;"/></a></p></li>
</ul>
<p>I removed the rear wheel and measured the distance from the wheel hub shaft (against which the bushings sit) to the surface of the ABS sensor ring, by first placing a straight-edge along the ABS sensor ring.</p>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/L5qWMcN.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/L5qWMcN.jpg" alt="measure malaligned rear wheel" style="width: 688px;"/></a></p>
<p>I first measured the distance from the bottom edge to the wheel hub shaft, using the factory wheel. The resulting distance is <code>18.93mm</code>.</p>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/yGZbZ9a.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/yGZbZ9a.jpg" alt="measure factory rear wheel" style="height: 688px;"/></a></p>
<p>Next, I measured the same distance for the warp9racing supplied rear wheel. The resulting distance is <code>20.84mm</code>.</p>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/VToToXx.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/VToToXx.jpg" alt="measure warp9racing rear wheel" style="height: 688px;"/></a></p>
<p>I then double-checked all measurements, supplied parts and considered other possible errors. I was left to conclude that the supplied rear wheel would not fit this motorcycle. I sent an email to warp9racing.com, while I set about making my own spacers that would put the rear wheel in its appropriate position, which is an extra <code>2mm</code> left.</p>
<p>I have <strong>still</strong> not heard from warp9racing since sending that email (20 December 2014), which is disappointing. Everything else about the company had been great, including the quality of the wheels. Unfortunately, since they now had my money, I was screwed. It was a shame to learn that warp9racing would not support their product. I suspect that nobody had actually successfully fitted these wheels to the 2014 model.</p>
<p>Oh well, plan B.</p>
<hr />
<p>Fortunately, I know an excellent machinist. Given the two supplied bushings, I asked him to add <code>2mm</code> to the right-sided one and shave <code>2mm</code> from the left-sided one.</p>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/eBL2HKX.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/eBL2HKX.jpg" alt="warp9racing bushings, before alteration" style="width: 688px;"/></a></p>
<p>Since he is awesome, this was not a problem and I had new bushings within a couple of hours.</p>
<p>I used the existing cush-drive rubber dampers and fitted them to the supermoto hub. This requires no bolts or fixings as they just slot right into position. Here they are on the factory hub.</p>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/MB9SzlJ.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/MB9SzlJ.jpg" alt="cush-drive rubber dampers" style="height: 688px;"/></a></p>
<p>Next, I fitted the warp9racing supplied 44T sprocket and cush-drive into the hub. Again, no fixings are required. After reassembling the rear wheel, with the custom-made bushings, it all slotted in perfectly. The alignment of the drive-chain and brake calipers was perfect.</p>
<h3 id="front-wheel-fitment">Front Wheel Fitment</h3>
<p>For the front wheel, I did not have the same problems with the bushings/spacers as I had for the rear wheel. In this case, the wheel fitted perfectly with the supplied spacers.</p>
<p>However, since the front wheel is wider than factory, it fouls on the fork leg protectors on both sides as well as the front brake hoses. The fork leg protectors are important and cannot be removed, as the left one retains the front brake hoses from hitting the wheel or rim.</p>
<p>Importantly, even though at rest the front wheel does not contact the front brake hose, <em>under motion, there is fouling</em>. Therefore, it is important to modify the left fork leg protector to clear the tyre as well as mount the front brake hoses on the outside of the fork leg protector. It is impossible for the forks to clear the brake hose if it were mounted in the original position, between the forks and the front wheel.</p>
<p>The fork leg protectors can be modified to clear the tyre by cutting a notch with a utility knife. The part number for the fork leg protectors, if you choose to have another set, is <code>7800109420030</code>.</p>
<p>Here is the modification of the right fork leg protector:</p>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/4XJDKqI.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/4XJDKqI.jpg" alt="right fork leg protector" style="height: 688px;"/></a></p>
<p>Here is the modification of the left fork leg protector:</p>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/5YN4qPW.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/5YN4qPW.jpg" alt="left fork leg protector" style="width: 688px;"/></a></p>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/wouBAt6.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/wouBAt6.jpg" alt="left fork leg protector" style="width: 688px;"/></a></p>
<p>The channeling that has been cut on the inside of the left fork leg protector is a consequence of having attempted to route the brake lines on the inside of the forks. It was then determined that this is impossible, since it fouls the forks when they are under compression.</p>
<h3 id="kickstand-height">Kickstand Height</h3>
<p>Using a factory kick stand, with the supermoto wheels fitted, the motorcycle will be difficult to stand on a level surface. This is because of the lowered overall height, requiring a shorter side stand.</p>
<p>Using an additional factory side stand (part <code>7650312300033</code>), I shortened it by <code>50mm</code>. After fitting the shortened side stand, the length was found to be optimal. I recommend losing exactly <code>50mm</code> from a factory side stand for this modification.</p>
<h3 id="speedometer">Speedometer</h3>
<p>With the supermoto wheels fitted, the speedometer will over-read by approximately <code>20%</code>. This can be corrected by paying a KTM service centre.</p>
<p>However, it can also be corrected with a minor modification to the factory wiring. This modification is simply a matter of disconnecting one wire from the harness. It should take a maximum of 15 minutes in total.</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Remove the headlight assembly.</li>
<li>Underneath the speedometer, on the right side, is a black rubber boot covering a white-coloured electrical plug. Disconnect this plug. There is a retainer on this plug, so don’t just pull it — undo the retainer.</li>
<li>Holding all the wires in the plug is a black-coloured retainer clip. Release this clip from the plug.</li>
<li>Identify the wire that is coloured completely brown, with no other trace colour.</li>
<li><p>Using nose pliers, gently pull this wire from the plug.</p>
<a href="http://i.imgur.com/x5SxCwq.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/x5SxCwq.jpg" alt="pulled brown wire" style="width: 688px;"/></a></li>
<li><p>Insulate this wire. I used 4mm heat-shrink.</p>
<a href="http://i.imgur.com/tHqHV8W.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/tHqHV8W.jpg" alt="insulated brown wire" style="width: 688px;"/></a></li>
<li>Restore the black-coloured retaining clip to the plug.</li>
<li>Reconnect the white-coloured plug to the speedometer and fit the protective rubber boot.</li>
<li>Turn the ignition to the <strong>ON</strong> position and wait for completion of the ignition start sequence.</li>
<li>By pressing the <strong>MODE</strong> button, scroll to the <strong>TRIP 1</strong> mode.</li>
<li>Hold down the <strong>MODE</strong> button for 10 seconds, until the dashboard displays the factory wheel length (<code>2250</code>), then release.</li>
<li><p>Using the <strong>MODE</strong> button to increase the wheel length and the <strong>SET</strong> button to decrease it, set the length to (<code>1840</code>).</p>
Be careful about holding down either of these two buttons for too long, since the scrolling speed increases rapidly.</li>
<li>Once the desired length has been selected, press the <strong>MODE</strong> and the <strong>SET</strong> buttons simultaneously, until the dashboard display returns to the <strong>TRIP 1</strong> mode.</li>
<li>Turn the ignition off and on to have the new settings take effect.</li>
<li><p>The time might have reset to <code>12:00</code>. Set the time to the current local time.</p>
<p>Here is the relevant excerpt from the Owner’s Manual (part <code>3213101en</code>)</p>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/6je7YXr.png"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/6je7YXr.png" alt="manual: set the time" style="width: 823px;"/></a></p></li>
</ol>
<p>Check the accuracy of the speedometer against a reliable GPS. At this setting, I found the accuracy to be within the tolerances of undetectable error.</p>
<h3 id="result">Result</h3>
<p>The wheels, with appropriate tyres, result in excellent handling of the motorcycle. I have run these same tyres on a track bike (YZF-R1) before and now with a lighter motorcycle, the performance is outstanding.</p>
<p>Wheelstands remain easy from third gear. Highway riding is still comfortable. The bike tracks exactly as it is told.</p>
<p>Here are some pictures.</p>
<hr />
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/Kcl2ODX.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/Kcl2ODX.jpg" alt="2014 KTM 690 Enduro R to Supermoto" style="width: 688px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/rzBoOJX.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/rzBoOJX.jpg" alt="2014 KTM 690 Enduro R to Supermoto" style="width: 688px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/Vbr0Zb2.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/Vbr0Zb2.jpg" alt="2014 KTM 690 Enduro R to Supermoto" style="width: 688px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/MfdQ1zw.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/MfdQ1zw.jpg" alt="2014 KTM 690 Enduro R to Supermoto" style="width: 688px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/9nLeT3t.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/9nLeT3t.jpg" alt="2014 KTM 690 Enduro R to Supermoto" style="width: 688px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/8KjaW8g.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/8KjaW8g.jpg" alt="2014 KTM 690 Enduro R to Supermoto" style="width: 688px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/eKTDTW1.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/eKTDTW1.jpg" alt="2014 KTM 690 Enduro R to Supermoto" style="width: 688px;"/></a></p>
<h3 id="list-of-existing-modifications">List of Existing Modifications</h3>
<p>It is not expected that any of these modifications have affected the procedures outlined here, however, they are listed for completeness.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>KTM bad fuel dongle (part <code>60312953000</code>)</p></li>
<li><p>Scotts <code>DS-SUB-3528-02R</code> steering stabilizer</p></li>
<li><p>Wings <code>690E/R 14+</code> muffler</p></li>
<li><p>Sicass Racing <code>22-100c</code> rear turn signals</p></li>
<li><p>Sicass Racing <code>22-206</code> black turn signal hand guard deflectors</p></li>
<li><p>(x4) Oledone <code>1L10-L</code> spotlights</p></li>
<li><p>Oxford <code>OXF.OF692Z</code> heated grips</p></li>
<li><p>Seat Concepts seat</p></li>
<li><p>Unifilter 690E (07-14) foam air filter</p></li>
<li><p>R&amp;G <code>FP0085BK</code> fork sliders</p></li>
<li><p>Rear swingarm spools</p></li>
<li><p>perunmoto KTM 690 subframe reinforcement kit</p></li>
<li><p>perunmoto KTM 690 Luggage rack</p></li>
<li><p>Barkbusters</p></li>
<li><p>KTM 690 Enduro 14L Safari Tanks long range fuel tank</p></li>
<li><p>(x2) 3BR 5V 2.1A USB charger</p></li>
<li><p>Doubletake mirrors with RAM mounts</p></li>
</ul>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>This service manual is made available online, in protest to a lack of response from KTM Australia, regarding a defective service manual product in violation of Australian Consumer Law (Schedule 2 of the Competition and Consumer Act 2010). Read more <a href="https://gist.github.com/tonymorris/d0b9cf9b0babde5df1cb">here</a>.<a href="#fnref1">↩</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>]]></summary>
</entry>

</feed>
