<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>λ Tony's blog λ — Posts tagged Motorcycling</title>
    <link href="http://blog.tmorris.net/tags/Motorcycling.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="http://blog.tmorris.net" />
    <id>http://blog.tmorris.net/tags/Motorcycling.xml</id>
    <author>
        <name>Tony Morris</name>
        <email>blog@tmorris.net</email>
    </author>
    <updated>2013-03-10T20:00:00Z</updated>
    <entry>
    <title>Lane-Splitting in Australia.</title>
    <link href="http://blog.tmorris.net/posts/lane-splitting/index.html" />
    <id>http://blog.tmorris.net/posts/lane-splitting/index.html</id>
    <published>2013-03-10T20:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-03-10T20:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The subject of lane-splitting on a motorcycle often comes up in discussion. In Australia, the legality of lane-splitting is not absolute. For example, under some circumstances, such as two (or even three) motorcycles sharing a lane, this manouvre may be legal (further specifics apply). Under some other circumstances, lane-splitting is illegal.</p>
<p>Below are verbatim excerpts of Transport Operations (Road Use Management) Act 1995; Transport Operations (Road Use Management-Road Rules) Regulation 1999 that are relevant to lane-splitting. The name of this legislation is sometimes abbreviated to <em>TORUM</em>. TORUM applies to the state of Queensland and is derived from the Australian Road Rules (ARR).</p>
<p>Other Australian state and territory road use legislation is also derived from the ARR. Although these sections have been excerpted directly from TORUM, they can also be found in the ARR (under the same sections) and also in the road use legislation for each Australian state/territory.</p>
<h1 id="no-overtaking-etc-to-the-left-of-a-vehicle">141 No overtaking etc to the left of a vehicle</h1>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>A driver (except the rider of a bicycle) must not overtake a vehicle to the left of the vehicle unless–
<ul>
<li>the driver is driving on a multi-lane road and the vehicle can be safely overtaken in a marked lane to the left of the vehicle; or</li>
<li>the vehicle is turning right, or making a U–turn from the centre of</li>
<li>the road, and is giving a right change of direction signal.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>The rider of a bicycle must not ride past, or overtake, to the left of a vehicle that is turning left and is giving a left change of direction signal.</li>
<li>In this section–
<ul>
<li>“turning right” does not include making a hook turn.</li>
<li>“vehicle” does not include a bus travelling along tram tracks, or any vehicle displaying a do not overtake turning vehicle sign.</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
<h1 id="no-overtaking-to-the-right-of-a-vehicle-turning-right-etc">142 No overtaking to the right of a vehicle turning right etc</h1>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>A driver must not overtake to the right of a vehicle if the vehicle is–
<ul>
<li>turning right or making a U-turn from the centre of the road; and</li>
<li>giving a right change of direction signal.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>In this section–
<ul>
<li>“turning right” does not include making a hook turn.</li>
<li>“vehicle” does not include a bus travelling along tram tracks, or any vehicle displaying a do not overtake turning vehicle sign.</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
<h1 id="driving-within-a-single-marked-lane-or-line-of-traffic">146 Driving within a single marked lane or line of traffic</h1>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>A driver on a multi-lane road must drive so the driver’s vehicle is completely in a marked lane, unless the driver is–
<ul>
<li>entering a part of the road of 1 kind from a part of the road of another kind (for example, moving to or from a service road, a shoulder of the road or emergency stopping lane); or</li>
<li>entering or leaving the road; or</li>
<li>moving from 1 marked lane to another marked lane; or</li>
<li>avoiding an obstruction; or</li>
<li>obeying a traffic control device applying to the marked lane; or</li>
<li>permitted to drive in more than 1 marked lane under this regulation.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>A driver on a road with 2 or more lines of traffic travelling in the same direction as the driver, but without marked lanes, must drive so the driver’s vehicle is completely in a single line of traffic unless–
<ul>
<li>it is not practicable to drive completely in a single line of traffic; or</li>
<li>the driver is entering a part of the road of 1 kind from a part of the road of another kind (for example, moving to or from a service road, a shoulder of the road or an emergency stopping lane); or</li>
<li>the driver is entering or leaving the road; or</li>
<li>the driver is moving from 1 line of traffic to another line of traffic; or</li>
<li>the driver is avoiding an obstruction.</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
<h1 id="moving-from-1-marked-lane-to-another-marked-lane-across-a-continuous-line-separating-the-lanes">147 Moving from 1 marked lane to another marked lane across a continuous line separating the lanes</h1>
<p>A driver on a multi-lane road must not move from 1 marked lane to another marked lane by crossing a continuous line separating the lanes unless–</p>
<ul>
<li>the driver is avoiding an obstruction; or</li>
<li>the driver is obeying a traffic control device applying to the first marked lane; or</li>
<li>the driver is permitted to drive in both marked lanes under this regulation; or</li>
<li>either of the marked lanes is a special purpose lane in which the driver is permitted to drive under this regulation and the driver is moving to or from the special purpose lane.</li>
</ul>
<h1 id="driving-on-or-across-a-continuous-white-edge-line">150 Driving on or across a continuous white edge line</h1>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>A driver must not drive on or over a continuous white edge line on a road unless the driver is–
<ul>
<li>turning at an intersection; or</li>
<li>entering or leaving the road; or</li>
<li>entering a part of the road of 1 kind from a part of the road of another kind (for example, moving to or from a service road, a shoulder of the road or an emergency stopping lane); or</li>
<li>overtaking a vehicle that is–
<ul>
<li>turning right or making a U-turn from the centre of the road; and</li>
<li>giving a right change of direction signal; or</li>
</ul></li>
<li>driving a slow-moving vehicle; or</li>
<li>stopping at the side of the road (including any shoulder of the road); or</li>
<li>driving a vehicle that is too wide, or too long, to drive on the road without driving on or over the edge line.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>This section does not apply to the rider of a bicycle or animal.</li>
</ol>
<h1 id="riding-a-motor-bike-or-bicycle-alongside-more-than-1-other-rider">151 Riding a motor bike or bicycle alongside more than 1 other rider</h1>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>The rider of a motor bike or bicycle must not ride on a road that is not a multi-lane road alongside more than 1 other rider, unless subsection (3) applies to the rider.</li>
<li>The rider of a motor bike or bicycle must not ride in a marked lane alongside more than 1 other rider in the marked lane, unless subsection (3) applies to the rider.</li>
<li>The rider of a motor bike or bicycle may ride alongside more than 1 other rider if the rider is overtaking the other riders.</li>
<li>If the rider of a motor bike or bicycle is riding on a road that is not a multi-lane road alongside another rider, or in a marked lane alongside another rider in the marked lane, the rider must ride not over 1.5 m from the other rider.</li>
<li>In this section–</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>“road” does not include a road-related area, but includes a bicycle path, a shared path and any shoulder of the road.</li>
</ul>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Safari Fuel Tanks -- Husqvarna TE510</title>
    <link href="http://blog.tmorris.net/posts/safari-fuel-tanks-husqvarna-te510/index.html" />
    <id>http://blog.tmorris.net/posts/safari-fuel-tanks-husqvarna-te510/index.html</id>
    <published>2010-10-26T19:57:36Z</published>
    <updated>2010-10-26T19:57:36Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.safaritanks.com.au/home/">Safari Tanks</a> recently released a long range fuel tank for the Husqvarna TE250/310/450/510 4-stroke enduro motorcycle. These bikes come standard with a 7.2 litre fuel tank, which simply does not cut the mustard, particularly for the thirsty 510.</p>
<p>I own a 2009 TE510 and a few weeks ago, I purchased <a href="http://www.safaritanks.com.au/home/14-Husqvarna/55-Husqvarna-TE250-310-450-510/flypage.tpl.html">this tank</a>. I was given the option of four colours: red, white, black or translucent. I chose white and I am happy with this choice. At this time, my bike had only done a few road kilometres and had not yet completed run-in.</p>
<p>Prior to my current TE510, I have owned other Husqvarna four stroke enduro motorcycles, but the TE510 is my first fuel-injected Husky. Below, I will attempt to write a balanced report of my experience with this product. Comments or questions are appreciated.</p>
<p>When it came time to fit the fuel tank, I found that the fuel pump did not install as specified and instead, could only fit in a 180 degree position. This is fine, except the supplied fuel line now did not reach the fuel tap outlet. Safari Tanks were quick to help me with this problem, spending a lot of time on the phone to resolve it (I live in Brisbane, about 1400km from Safari headquarters). Safari supplied me (express postage) with a suitable fuel line for the altered fuel pump fitting after I provided the measurements. This fuel line met my specifications and fit perfectly.</p>
<p>The <a href="http://safaritanksusa.com/Husqvarna%20Front.pdf">supplied instructions</a> did not mention that the side radiator guards (not the fins) must be removed, however this was pretty obvious since the tank was not going on otherwise. The fuel tank appears to provide better protection from side impact than the original guards as well. The stock radiator fins did not require any modification at all.</p>
<p>I had trouble fitting the seat since the seat post was a little too far posterior, so I removed the seat post. This allowed the seat to install perfectly.</p>
<p>As for the performance of the tank I cannot speak highly enough. After recently spending a 3-day weekend riding in a <a href="http://osm.org/go/ueGXNhZb-">massive state forest</a>, I didn’t once come even close to hitting reserve on the 510, nor did I ever fill the tank (to keep weight down). The tank is simply enormous and this attracted comments from other riders, even though it blends well with the bike’s styling.</p>
<p>However, aside from the extra weight of carrying more fuel, the ergonomics of the tank are indistinguishable from the original tank and it allows you to adopt a correct riding position even in aggressive riding. I was quite impressed with this obviously clever design given the massive increase in fuel range. I expect this is because the extra fuel capacity is below the typical fuel tank position.</p>
<p>The (supplied) fittings and mountings for the tank are very strong, particularly for the frame mount, and even after some hard riding (to give you an idea, I wrote off the stock tyre in 15 minutes) there was no sign of fatigue.</p>
<p>After going riding with my mates on a 510 race-style enduro with a 7.2 litre tank, it’s usually me who is the first to complain of the need to return to a fuel supply. Not anymore, not even close. I’m very happy with the purchase of the Safari fuel tank and I would recommend it to anyone. After dealing with some minor fitting issues and the obvious attention given to my complaints, I have no doubt that Safari will have sorted out those issues by now. I would recommend this fuel tank to any fellow enthusiast of Husqvarna high-performance motorcycles.</p>
<p>Some pictures of the bike fitted with the tank follow.</p>
<div class="figure">
<img src="http://i.imgur.com/0eWAR.jpg" alt="Husqvarna TE510 Safari Fuel Tank" /><p class="caption">Husqvarna TE510 Safari Fuel Tank</p>
</div>
<div class="figure">
<img src="http://i.imgur.com/YFZ09.jpg" alt="Husqvarna TE510 Safari Fuel Tank" /><p class="caption">Husqvarna TE510 Safari Fuel Tank</p>
</div>
<div class="figure">
<img src="http://i.imgur.com/uJybZ.jpg" alt="Husqvarna TE510 Safari Fuel Tank" /><p class="caption">Husqvarna TE510 Safari Fuel Tank</p>
</div>
<div class="figure">
<img src="http://i.imgur.com/ns6ZD.jpg" alt="Husqvarna TE510 Safari Fuel Tank" /><p class="caption">Husqvarna TE510 Safari Fuel Tank</p>
</div>
<div class="figure">
<img src="http://i.imgur.com/Qp61g.jpg" alt="Husqvarna TE510 Safari Fuel Tank" /><p class="caption">Husqvarna TE510 Safari Fuel Tank</p>
</div>
<div class="figure">
<img src="http://i.imgur.com/WSDmo.jpg" alt="Husqvarna TE510 Safari Fuel Tank" /><p class="caption">Husqvarna TE510 Safari Fuel Tank</p>
</div>]]></summary>
</entry>

</feed>
