<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>λ Tony's blog λ — Posts tagged Motorcycling</title>
    <link href="http://blog.tmorris.net/tags/Motorcycling.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="http://blog.tmorris.net" />
    <id>http://blog.tmorris.net/tags/Motorcycling.xml</id>
    <author>
        <name>Tony Morris</name>
        <email>blog@tmorris.net</email>
    </author>
    <updated>2015-01-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <entry>
    <title>2014 KTM 690 Enduro to Supermoto</title>
    <link href="http://blog.tmorris.net/posts/ktm690-enduro-smc/index.html" />
    <id>http://blog.tmorris.net/posts/ktm690-enduro-smc/index.html</id>
    <published>2015-01-07T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-01-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This article is a description of the conversion of a 2014 KTM 690 Enduro R to a Supermoto with 17&quot; wheels. Two goals are kept in mind:</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li><p>It is easy to go back to Enduro configuration.</p></li>
<li><p>It is easy to go back to factory. This refers to minimising the irreversible modification of factory parts.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>Part names and numbers will be provided.</p>
<p>If you would like me to do this conversion for on your bike and you are able to transport your motorcycle to Brisbane, please email me and I will be happy to help you.</p>
<p><a href="tonymorris@gmail.com" class="uri">tonymorris@gmail.com</a></p>
<h3 id="motorcycle-models">Motorcycle models</h3>
<p>The motorcycle was already heavily modified (details below). It is an Australian version of the KTM 690 Enduro R, which closely resembles the EU version. I would expect that the modification described here would apply, without alteration, to US models.</p>
<p>I also expect that this description would apply to earlier year models, with exception for taking into account the ABS. The use of ABS in the 2014 model only changes the following facts:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>There is no need to purchase the ABS sensor rings for the supermoto wheels.</p></li>
<li><p>The earlier models use different wheel bushing/spacer widths, which:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>are supplied with the supermoto wheels for all year models</p></li>
<li><p>required customisation for the rear wheel in my case anyway</p></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<h3 id="wheels">Wheels</h3>
<p>In August 2014, I purchased the front wheel, rear wheel and cush-drive hub with 44T sprocket from <a href="http://www.warp9racing.com/sm_wheels_KTM.html">warp9racing.com</a>:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>ASSEMBLED KTM 690 FRONT WHEEL - 17“X3.50” BLACK HUB / BLACK RIM / SILVER SPOKES WITH SILVER NIPPLES INCLUDES 300MM FLOATING ROTOR WITH SPACERS</p>
<p><code>USD468.00</code></p></li>
<li><p>ASSEMBLED KTM 690 ENDURO REAR WHEEL - 17“X4.25” ORANGE HUB / BLACK RIM / SILVER SPOKES WITH SILVER NIPPLES INCLUDES ROTOR</p>
<p><code>USD468.00</code></p></li>
<li><p>KTM 690 CUSH DRIVE WITH SPROCKET (USES OEM RUBBERS) 44T</p>
<p><code>USD139.00</code></p></li>
</ul>
<hr />
<p>When the wheels arrived, they looked like this:</p>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/rmurQaG.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/rmurQaG.jpg" alt="warp9racing supermoto wheels" style="width: 1032px;"/></a></p>
<p>Note that the wheels included:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>disc brakes</p></li>
<li><p>wheel bushings/spacers</p></li>
</ul>
<h3 id="abs-sensor-rings">ABS Sensor Rings</h3>
<p>I chose to buy a second set of ABS sensor rings and factory bolts to use on the supermoto wheels, so that I didn’t have to remove them whenever I wanted to go back to Enduro configuration.</p>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>1x</strong> SENSOR WHEEL FRONT (KTM part <code>60142020000</code>)</p>
<p><code>USD23.46</code></p></li>
<li><p><strong>1x</strong> SENSOR WHEEL ABS REAR (KTM part <code>76542021000</code>)</p>
<p><code>USD23.36</code></p></li>
<li><p><strong>15x</strong> ZYL.SCHRAUBE DIN14580 M6X16 (KTM part <code>014580060166S</code>)</p>
<p><code>USD11.25</code> (<code>USD0.79</code> each)</p></li>
</ul>
<hr />
<p>Each ABS sensor requires six (6) of the Zylinderkopf DIN14580 Torx bolts. I purchased a total of fifteen (15) so that I had 3 spares.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://github.com/tonymorris/ktm690/blob/master/manuals.md">KTM 690 service manual</a><a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"><sup>1</sup></a> specifies the following for these bolts:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Tighten to 14Nm (10.3 lbf·ft) torque</p></li>
<li><p>Use Loctite 243 (thread locker)</p></li>
<li><p>“The lettering on the ABS sensor wheel is located on the outside.”</p></li>
</ul>
<hr />
<p>After fitment of the ABS sensor rings, the wheels now look like this:</p>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/oP0tzZI.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/oP0tzZI.jpg" alt="warp9racing supermoto wheels, with ABS sensor" style="width: 1032px;"/></a></p>
<h1 id="tyres">Tyres</h1>
<p>I fitted Pirelli Diablo Rosso tyres to the rims. The tyre sizes were chosen for their application, however, it was later learned that the size is also important for fitment. Specifically, the front tyre is at the limit of maximum width without fouling.</p>
<p>I also used tubes and rim bands.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Front <code>150/60-ZR17</code></p></li>
<li><p>Rear <code>120/70-ZR17</code></p></li>
</ul>
<h1 id="rear-wheel-fitment">Rear Wheel Fitment</h1>
<p>Using the warp9racing supplied bushings, I was able to fit the rear wheel, however, it was clearly malaligned, since:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>the inside brake pad friction was preventing wheel rotation</p></li>
<li><p>the ABS sensor ring bolt heads fouled the rear brake caliper</p>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/zaIwNkG.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/zaIwNkG.jpg" alt="warp9racing supermoto rear wheel, malaligned" style="height: 1033px;"/></a></p></li>
</ul>
<p>I removed the rear wheel and measured the distance from the wheel hub shaft (against which the bushings sit) to the surface of the ABS sensor ring, by first placing a straight-edge along the ABS sensor ring.</p>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/L5qWMcN.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/L5qWMcN.jpg" alt="measure malaligned rear wheel" style="width: 688px;"/></a></p>
<p>I first measured the distance from the bottom edge to the wheel hub shaft, using the factory wheel. The resulting distance is <code>18.93mm</code>.</p>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/yGZbZ9a.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/yGZbZ9a.jpg" alt="measure factory rear wheel" style="height: 688px;"/></a></p>
<p>Next, I measured the same distance for the warp9racing supplied rear wheel. The resulting distance is <code>20.84mm</code>.</p>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/VToToXx.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/VToToXx.jpg" alt="measure warp9racing rear wheel" style="height: 688px;"/></a></p>
<p>I then double-checked all measurements, supplied parts and considered other possible errors. I was left to conclude that the supplied rear wheel would not fit this motorcycle. I sent an email to warp9racing.com, while I set about making my own spacers that would put the rear wheel in its appropriate position, which is an extra <code>2mm</code> left.</p>
<p>I have <strong>still</strong> not heard from warp9racing since sending that email (20 December 2014), which is disappointing. Everything else about the company had been great, including the quality of the wheels. Unfortunately, since they now had my money, I was screwed. It was a shame to learn that warp9racing would not support their product. I suspect that nobody had actually successfully fitted these wheels to the 2014 model.</p>
<p>Oh well, plan B.</p>
<hr />
<p>Fortunately, I know an excellent machinist. Given the two supplied bushings, I asked him to add <code>2mm</code> to the right-sided one and shave <code>2mm</code> from the left-sided one.</p>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/eBL2HKX.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/eBL2HKX.jpg" alt="warp9racing bushings, before alteration" style="width: 688px;"/></a></p>
<p>Since he is awesome, this was not a problem and I had new bushings within a couple of hours.</p>
<p>I used the existing cush-drive rubber dampers and fitted them to the supermoto hub. This requires no bolts or fixings as they just slot right into position. Here they are on the factory hub.</p>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/MB9SzlJ.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/MB9SzlJ.jpg" alt="cush-drive rubber dampers" style="height: 688px;"/></a></p>
<p>Next, I fitted the warp9racing supplied 44T sprocket and cush-drive into the hub. Again, no fixings are required. After reassembling the rear wheel, with the custom-made bushings, it all slotted in perfectly. The alignment of the drive-chain and brake calipers was perfect.</p>
<h3 id="front-wheel-fitment">Front Wheel Fitment</h3>
<p>For the front wheel, I did not have the same problems with the bushings/spacers as I had for the rear wheel. In this case, the wheel fitted perfectly with the supplied spacers.</p>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col width="8%" />
</colgroup>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td align="left">However, since the front wheel is wider than factory, it fouls on the fork leg protectors on both sides as well as the front brake hoses. The fork leg protectors are important and cannot be removed, as the left one retains the front brake hoses from hitting the wheel or rim.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td align="left">Importantly, even though at rest the front wheel does not contact the front brake hose, <em>under motion, there is fouling</em>. Therefore, it is important to modify the left fork leg protector to clear the tyre as well as mount the front brake hoses on the outside of the fork leg protector. It is impossible for the forks to clear the brake hose if it were mounted in the original position, between the forks and the front wheel.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td align="left">The fork leg protectors can be modified to clear the tyre by cutting a notch with a utility knife. The part number for the fork leg protectors, if you choose to have another set, is <code>7800109420030</code>.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td align="left">Here is the modification of the right fork leg protector:</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td align="left"><a href="http://i.imgur.com/4XJDKqI.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/4XJDKqI.jpg" alt="right fork leg protector" style="height: 688px;"/></a></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td align="left">Here is the modification of the left fork leg protector:</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td align="left"><a href="http://i.imgur.com/5YN4qPW.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/5YN4qPW.jpg" alt="left fork leg protector" style="width: 688px;"/></a></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td align="left"><a href="http://i.imgur.com/wouBAt6.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/wouBAt6.jpg" alt="left fork leg protector" style="width: 688px;"/></a></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td align="left">Note the channeling that has been cut into the fork leg protector to re-route the front brake hoses. This is in addition to the notch that has also been cut to clear the tyre. This modification to the fork leg protector is necessary to prevent fouling through the entire suspension travel.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td align="left">Using the factory front brake hose position, it will not foul the rim while at rest. However, it was quickly found to foul during operation of the motorcycle. This is why the additional channeling has been notched into the left fork leg protector.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td align="left"><a href="http://i.imgur.com/JjojyyP.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/JjojyyP.jpg" alt="left fork leg protector" style="height: 688px;"/></a></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h3 id="kickstand-height">Kickstand Height</h3>
<p>Using a factory kick stand, with the supermoto wheels fitted, the motorcycle will be difficult to stand on a level surface. This is because of the lowered overall height, requiring a shorter side stand.</p>
<p>Using an additional factory side stand (part <code>7650312300033</code>), I shortened it by <code>50mm</code>. After fitting the shortened side stand, the length was found to be optimal. I recommend losing exactly <code>50mm</code> from a factory side stand for this modification.</p>
<h3 id="speedometer">Speedometer</h3>
<p>With the supermoto wheels fitted, the speedometer will over-read by approximately <code>20%</code>. This can be corrected by paying a KTM service centre.</p>
<p>However, it can also be corrected with a minor modification to the factory wiring. This modification is simply a matter of disconnecting one wire from the harness. It should take a maximum of 15 minutes in total.</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Remove the headlight assembly.</li>
<li>Underneath the speedometer, on the right side, is a black rubber boot covering a white-coloured electrical plug. Disconnect this plug. There is a retainer on this plug, so don’t just pull it — undo the retainer.</li>
<li>Holding all the wires in the plug is a black-coloured retainer clip. Release this clip from the plug.</li>
<li>Identify the wire that is coloured completely brown, with no other trace colour.</li>
<li><p>Using nose pliers, gently pull this wire from the plug.</p>
<a href="http://i.imgur.com/x5SxCwq.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/x5SxCwq.jpg" alt="pulled brown wire" style="width: 688px;"/></a></li>
<li><p>Insulate this wire. I used 4mm heat-shrink.</p>
<a href="http://i.imgur.com/tHqHV8W.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/tHqHV8W.jpg" alt="insulated brown wire" style="width: 688px;"/></a></li>
<li>Restore the black-coloured retaining clip to the plug.</li>
<li>Reconnect the white-coloured plug to the speedometer and fit the protective rubber boot.</li>
<li>Turn the ignition to the <strong>ON</strong> position and wait for completion of the ignition start sequence.</li>
<li>By pressing the <strong>MODE</strong> button, scroll to the <strong>TRIP 1</strong> mode.</li>
<li>Hold down the <strong>MODE</strong> button for 10 seconds, until the dashboard displays the factory wheel length (<code>2250</code>), then release.</li>
<li><p>Using the <strong>MODE</strong> button to increase the wheel length and the <strong>SET</strong> button to decrease it, set the length to (<code>1840</code>).</p>
Be careful about holding down either of these two buttons for too long, since the scrolling speed increases rapidly.</li>
<li>Once the desired length has been selected, press the <strong>MODE</strong> and the <strong>SET</strong> buttons simultaneously, until the dashboard display returns to the <strong>TRIP 1</strong> mode.</li>
<li><p>The time will have reset to <code>12:00</code>. Set the time to the current local time.</p>
<p>Here is the relevant excerpt from the Owner’s Manual (part <code>3213101en</code>)</p>
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/6je7YXr.png"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/6je7YXr.png" alt="manual: set the time" style="width: 823px;"/></a></p></li>
</ol>
<p>Check the accuracy of the speedometer against a reliable GPS. At this setting, I found the accuracy to be within the tolerances of undetectable error.</p>
<h3 id="result">Result</h3>
<p>The wheels, with appropriate tyres, result in excellent handling of the motorcycle. I have run these same tyres on a track bike (YZF-R1) before and now with a lighter motorcycle, the performance is outstanding.</p>
<p>Wheelstands remain easy from third gear. Highway riding is still comfortable. The bike tracks exactly as it is told.</p>
<p>Here are some pictures.</p>
<hr />
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/Kcl2ODX.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/Kcl2ODX.jpg" alt="2014 KTM 690 Enduro R to Supermoto" style="width: 688px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/rzBoOJX.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/rzBoOJX.jpg" alt="2014 KTM 690 Enduro R to Supermoto" style="width: 688px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/Vbr0Zb2.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/Vbr0Zb2.jpg" alt="2014 KTM 690 Enduro R to Supermoto" style="width: 688px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/MfdQ1zw.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/MfdQ1zw.jpg" alt="2014 KTM 690 Enduro R to Supermoto" style="width: 688px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/9nLeT3t.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/9nLeT3t.jpg" alt="2014 KTM 690 Enduro R to Supermoto" style="width: 688px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/8KjaW8g.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/8KjaW8g.jpg" alt="2014 KTM 690 Enduro R to Supermoto" style="width: 688px;"/></a></p>
<hr />
<p><a href="http://i.imgur.com/eKTDTW1.jpg"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/eKTDTW1.jpg" alt="2014 KTM 690 Enduro R to Supermoto" style="width: 688px;"/></a></p>
<h3 id="list-of-existing-modifications">List of Existing Modifications</h3>
<p>It is not expected that any of these modifications have affected the procedures outlined here, however, they are listed for completeness.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>KTM bad fuel dongle (part <code>60312953000</code>)</p></li>
<li><p>Scotts <code>DS-SUB-3528-02R</code> steering stabilizer</p></li>
<li><p>Wings <code>690E/R 14+</code> muffler</p></li>
<li><p>Sicass Racing <code>22-100c</code> rear turn signals</p></li>
<li><p>Sicass Racing <code>22-206</code> black turn signal hand guard deflectors</p></li>
<li><p>(x4) Oledone <code>1L10-L</code> spotlights</p></li>
<li><p>Oxford <code>OXF.OF692Z</code> heated grips</p></li>
<li><p>Seat Concepts seat</p></li>
<li><p>Unifilter 690E (07-14) foam air filter</p></li>
<li><p>R&amp;G <code>FP0085BK</code> fork sliders</p></li>
<li><p>Rear swingarm spools</p></li>
<li><p>perunmoto KTM 690 subframe reinforcement kit</p></li>
<li><p>perunmoto KTM 690 Luggage rack</p></li>
<li><p>Barkbusters</p></li>
<li><p>KTM 690 Enduro 14L Safari Tanks long range fuel tank</p></li>
<li><p>(x2) 3BR 5V 2.1A USB charger</p></li>
<li><p>Doubletake mirrors with RAM mounts</p></li>
</ul>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>This service manual is made available online, in protest to a lack of response from KTM Australia, regarding a defective service manual product in violation of Australian Consumer Law (Schedule 2 of the Competition and Consumer Act 2010). Read more <a href="https://gist.github.com/tonymorris/d0b9cf9b0babde5df1cb">here</a>.<a href="#fnref1">↩</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Brisbane Ride Spots</title>
    <link href="http://blog.tmorris.net/posts/brisbane-ride-spots/index.html" />
    <id>http://blog.tmorris.net/posts/brisbane-ride-spots/index.html</id>
    <published>2014-10-13T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2014-10-13T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently, on a forum, I saw a question regarding dirt bike areas around Brisbane. The question was motivated by a licenced rider on a registered motorcycle (WR450F), looking for areas to explore. I gave the following answer and I intend to update the answer with any improvements here.</p>
<hr />
<p>I do surveying as a hobby and have completed every state-owned track within about 250km of Brisbane (and some beyond, mostly northern Queensland). I have released that data openly under the OpenStreetMap project and I do public releases for use in Garmin devices. There are also phone apps for using this data. Some of those tracks are now not legally traversable, even for registered bikes. I started doing this several years ago.</p>
<p>The project has a map viewable at <a href="http://osm.org/" class="uri">http://osm.org/</a> This map is also available on the <a href="http://osmand.net/">OsmAnd</a> application for android. I have friends that run it on iphone, but every time I ask them how to recommend it to iphone users, I get some unusable answer, so <em>shrug</em> don’t know :)</p>
<p>For running it on Garmin devices, it requires a bit of technical understanding and my map build is rather custom. For example, I also like to walk up hills around here (e.g. Mt Barney), so my build includes a topographic map of those areas of interest. I also run a custom filter on the data before the build to correct errors according to my own standards. I prefer using a device with an accurate antenna (which is also very expensive!), but using a phone is just fine for user application (opposed to surveying).</p>
<p>Well, here are some riding spots, just from the top of my head. They all have various levels of difficulty and some of them are not always completely open to access. Sometimes they are not open at all (e.g. during the 2011 flood). Also note that there are some people who think that “giving away our secret riding areas is reprehensible!” Ignore them, they don’t realise it’s not a secret and never was. Self-importance bores me.</p>
<hr />
<h3 id="north-of-brisbane">North of Brisbane</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://www.openstreetmap.org/#map=14/-27.1162/152.6851">Mount Mee State Forest</a> Mostly fire trails now. Look out for 4x4. A lot of excellent enduro tracks that are now illegal to traverse. There is still one remaining, that can be used by motorcycles, but not 4x4. There is also a now-closed logging area, that the government has promised to reopen one day. We’ll see.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.openstreetmap.org/#map=14/-26.9557/152.8996">Beerburrum State Forest</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.openstreetmap.org/#map=14/-26.8806/152.8505">Peachester State Forest</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.openstreetmap.org/#map=13/-26.8604/152.6645">Bellthorpe State Forest</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.openstreetmap.org/#map=13/-26.7422/152.5282">Conondale National Park</a> Also, <a href="http://tonymorris.github.io/blog/posts/ride-report-mubbip-woo/index.html">here is a funny story about a ride in there last Christmas</a>.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.openstreetmap.org/#map=13/-26.5188/152.5939">Imbil State Forest</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.openstreetmap.org/#map=13/-26.3605/152.5462">Amamoor State Forest</a> My favourite. Has some excellent and challenging enduro.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.openstreetmap.org/#map=13/-26.0498/153.0461">Great Sandy National Park</a> Just like the label, lots of sand. Beach riding nearby too. Vehicle access permit is required in some areas (it’s cheap and easy to do online or purchase at Rainbow Beach).</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.openstreetmap.org/#map=13/-25.4509/153.0454">Great Sandy National Park (Fraser Island)</a> Well, it’s Fraser Island, so expect transport across the water and lots and lots and lots of sand. Permit required.</p></li>
</ul>
<hr />
<h3 id="south-of-brisbane">South of Brisbane</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://www.openstreetmap.org/#map=15/-28.1595/153.0525">Duck Creek Road</a> A mild and scenic ascent from Kerry up to O’Reilly’s. Excellent for a short trip out. I have seen less-experienced riders do it on a Triumph 1200. Look out for 4x4.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.openstreetmap.org/#map=13/-28.3947/153.0416">Border Ranges National Park</a> A great day trip, scenic rainforest ride that extends for hours. Great for all rider skill levels. Dead easy for a learner, and good fun and scenic if you are not.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.openstreetmap.org/#map=14/-28.5314/152.5193">Tooloom State Forest</a> Fire trails, with some harder off shoots.</p></li>
</ul>
<hr />
<h3 id="west-of-brisbane">West of Brisbane</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://www.openstreetmap.org/#map=13/-28.5716/151.8079">Passchendaele State Forest</a> Another favourite. Most scenic and some challenging areas. Dropping your bike will cost some $$ on those rocks (it ain’t called the granite belt for nothing).</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.openstreetmap.org/#map=13/-28.8624/151.6590">Sundown National Park</a> Some harder trails and technical hill climbs. Rocky, very scenic. Look out for 4x4.</p></li>
</ul>
<hr />
<h3 id="a-couple-of-short-videos">A couple of short videos</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jaGwoibQH38&amp;list=UUpDeRLsIqd041pueRjRUY0Q">Passchendaele State Forest 23 August 2014</a> We had the forest to ourselves.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=g-Qpe7ZJZIg">My friend making a graceful entrance onto Rainbow Beach</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=b2DW6OzLXc8">Another friend on a fire trail with a 800XC in Mount Mee State Forest</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Mg9gWIHjymY">My unwelcome encounter with a red-bellied black snake in Beerburrum State Forest</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://vimeo.com/45384135">My friend going arse up on his TTR250 at Emu Creek Extreme Retreat</a> This area is near Urbenville and Tooloom State Forest. It is a privately owned track and does not require a registered bike. Good if you have friends on motocrossers or something. My friend is in fact, upside-down in the water and after a few seconds of laughing, I started wondering if he was going to pop back up.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://vimeo.com/29880420">Sundown National Park 3 years ago</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://vimeo.com/24759031">Mount Mee State Forest 3 years ago</a> It is also my first video compilation, so I pressed all the fancy buttons.</p></li>
</ul>
<hr />
<p>I have certainly left areas some off, but let’s not be greedy :)</p>
<p>In any case, we should just meet up, work out what you are looking for and go for a ride. Unfortunately though, I am dealing with some health issues at the moment and hope to be back on two wheels by December.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Lane-Splitting in Australia.</title>
    <link href="http://blog.tmorris.net/posts/lane-splitting/index.html" />
    <id>http://blog.tmorris.net/posts/lane-splitting/index.html</id>
    <published>2013-03-10T20:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-03-10T20:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The subject of lane-splitting on a motorcycle often comes up in discussion. In Australia, the legality of lane-splitting is not absolute. For example, under some circumstances, such as two (or even three) motorcycles sharing a lane, this manouvre may be legal (further specifics apply). Under some other circumstances, lane-splitting is illegal.</p>
<p>Below are verbatim excerpts of Transport Operations (Road Use Management) Act 1995; Transport Operations (Road Use Management-Road Rules) Regulation 1999 that are relevant to lane-splitting. The name of this legislation is sometimes abbreviated to <em>TORUM</em>. TORUM applies to the state of Queensland and is derived from the Australian Road Rules (ARR).</p>
<p>Other Australian state and territory road use legislation is also derived from the ARR. Although these sections have been excerpted directly from TORUM, they can also be found in the ARR (under the same sections) and also in the road use legislation for other Australian states and territories.</p>
<h1 id="no-overtaking-etc-to-the-left-of-a-vehicle">141 No overtaking etc to the left of a vehicle</h1>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>A driver (except the rider of a bicycle) must not overtake a vehicle to the left of the vehicle unless–
<ul>
<li>the driver is driving on a multi-lane road and the vehicle can be safely overtaken in a marked lane to the left of the vehicle; or</li>
<li>the vehicle is turning right, or making a U–turn from the centre of</li>
<li>the road, and is giving a right change of direction signal.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>The rider of a bicycle must not ride past, or overtake, to the left of a vehicle that is turning left and is giving a left change of direction signal.</li>
<li>In this section–
<ul>
<li>“turning right” does not include making a hook turn.</li>
<li>“vehicle” does not include a bus travelling along tram tracks, or any vehicle displaying a do not overtake turning vehicle sign.</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
<h1 id="no-overtaking-to-the-right-of-a-vehicle-turning-right-etc">142 No overtaking to the right of a vehicle turning right etc</h1>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>A driver must not overtake to the right of a vehicle if the vehicle is–
<ul>
<li>turning right or making a U-turn from the centre of the road; and</li>
<li>giving a right change of direction signal.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>In this section–
<ul>
<li>“turning right” does not include making a hook turn.</li>
<li>“vehicle” does not include a bus travelling along tram tracks, or any vehicle displaying a do not overtake turning vehicle sign.</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
<h1 id="driving-within-a-single-marked-lane-or-line-of-traffic">146 Driving within a single marked lane or line of traffic</h1>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>A driver on a multi-lane road must drive so the driver’s vehicle is completely in a marked lane, unless the driver is–
<ul>
<li>entering a part of the road of 1 kind from a part of the road of another kind (for example, moving to or from a service road, a shoulder of the road or emergency stopping lane); or</li>
<li>entering or leaving the road; or</li>
<li>moving from 1 marked lane to another marked lane; or</li>
<li>avoiding an obstruction; or</li>
<li>obeying a traffic control device applying to the marked lane; or</li>
<li>permitted to drive in more than 1 marked lane under this regulation.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>A driver on a road with 2 or more lines of traffic travelling in the same direction as the driver, but without marked lanes, must drive so the driver’s vehicle is completely in a single line of traffic unless–
<ul>
<li>it is not practicable to drive completely in a single line of traffic; or</li>
<li>the driver is entering a part of the road of 1 kind from a part of the road of another kind (for example, moving to or from a service road, a shoulder of the road or an emergency stopping lane); or</li>
<li>the driver is entering or leaving the road; or</li>
<li>the driver is moving from 1 line of traffic to another line of traffic; or</li>
<li>the driver is avoiding an obstruction.</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
<h1 id="moving-from-1-marked-lane-to-another-marked-lane-across-a-continuous-line-separating-the-lanes">147 Moving from 1 marked lane to another marked lane across a continuous line separating the lanes</h1>
<p>A driver on a multi-lane road must not move from 1 marked lane to another marked lane by crossing a continuous line separating the lanes unless–</p>
<ul>
<li>the driver is avoiding an obstruction; or</li>
<li>the driver is obeying a traffic control device applying to the first marked lane; or</li>
<li>the driver is permitted to drive in both marked lanes under this regulation; or</li>
<li>either of the marked lanes is a special purpose lane in which the driver is permitted to drive under this regulation and the driver is moving to or from the special purpose lane.</li>
</ul>
<h1 id="driving-on-or-across-a-continuous-white-edge-line">150 Driving on or across a continuous white edge line</h1>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>A driver must not drive on or over a continuous white edge line on a road unless the driver is–
<ul>
<li>turning at an intersection; or</li>
<li>entering or leaving the road; or</li>
<li>entering a part of the road of 1 kind from a part of the road of another kind (for example, moving to or from a service road, a shoulder of the road or an emergency stopping lane); or</li>
<li>overtaking a vehicle that is–
<ul>
<li>turning right or making a U-turn from the centre of the road; and</li>
<li>giving a right change of direction signal; or</li>
</ul></li>
<li>driving a slow-moving vehicle; or</li>
<li>stopping at the side of the road (including any shoulder of the road); or</li>
<li>driving a vehicle that is too wide, or too long, to drive on the road without driving on or over the edge line.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>This section does not apply to the rider of a bicycle or animal.</li>
</ol>
<h1 id="riding-a-motor-bike-or-bicycle-alongside-more-than-1-other-rider">151 Riding a motor bike or bicycle alongside more than 1 other rider</h1>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>The rider of a motor bike or bicycle must not ride on a road that is not a multi-lane road alongside more than 1 other rider, unless subsection (3) applies to the rider.</li>
<li>The rider of a motor bike or bicycle must not ride in a marked lane alongside more than 1 other rider in the marked lane, unless subsection (3) applies to the rider.</li>
<li>The rider of a motor bike or bicycle may ride alongside more than 1 other rider if the rider is overtaking the other riders.</li>
<li>If the rider of a motor bike or bicycle is riding on a road that is not a multi-lane road alongside another rider, or in a marked lane alongside another rider in the marked lane, the rider must ride not over 1.5 m from the other rider.</li>
<li>In this section–</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>“road” does not include a road-related area, but includes a bicycle path, a shared path and any shoulder of the road.</li>
</ul>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Safari Fuel Tanks -- Husqvarna TE510</title>
    <link href="http://blog.tmorris.net/posts/safari-fuel-tanks-husqvarna-te510/index.html" />
    <id>http://blog.tmorris.net/posts/safari-fuel-tanks-husqvarna-te510/index.html</id>
    <published>2010-10-26T19:57:36Z</published>
    <updated>2010-10-26T19:57:36Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.safaritanks.com.au/home/">Safari Tanks</a> recently released a long range fuel tank for the Husqvarna TE250/310/450/510 4-stroke enduro motorcycle. These bikes come standard with a 7.2 litre fuel tank, which simply does not cut the mustard, particularly for the thirsty 510.</p>
<p>I own a 2009 TE510 and a few weeks ago, I purchased <a href="http://www.safaritanks.com.au/home/14-Husqvarna/55-Husqvarna-TE250-310-450-510/flypage.tpl.html">this tank</a>. I was given the option of four colours: red, white, black or translucent. I chose white and I am happy with this choice. At this time, my bike had only done a few road kilometres and had not yet completed run-in.</p>
<p>Prior to my current TE510, I have owned other Husqvarna four stroke enduro motorcycles, but the TE510 is my first fuel-injected Husky. Below, I will attempt to write a balanced report of my experience with this product. Comments or questions are appreciated.</p>
<p>When it came time to fit the fuel tank, I found that the fuel pump did not install as specified and instead, could only fit in a 180 degree position. This is fine, except the supplied fuel line now did not reach the fuel tap outlet. Safari Tanks were quick to help me with this problem, spending a lot of time on the phone to resolve it (I live in Brisbane, about 1400km from Safari headquarters). Safari supplied me (express postage) with a suitable fuel line for the altered fuel pump fitting after I provided the measurements. This fuel line met my specifications and fit perfectly.</p>
<p>The <a href="http://safaritanksusa.com/Husqvarna%20Front.pdf">supplied instructions</a> did not mention that the side radiator guards (not the fins) must be removed, however this was pretty obvious since the tank was not going on otherwise. The fuel tank appears to provide better protection from side impact than the original guards as well. The stock radiator fins did not require any modification at all.</p>
<p>I had trouble fitting the seat since the seat post was a little too far posterior, so I removed the seat post. This allowed the seat to install perfectly.</p>
<p>As for the performance of the tank I cannot speak highly enough. After recently spending a 3-day weekend riding in a <a href="http://osm.org/go/ueGXNhZb-">massive state forest</a>, I didn’t once come even close to hitting reserve on the 510, nor did I ever fill the tank (to keep weight down). The tank is simply enormous and this attracted comments from other riders, even though it blends well with the bike’s styling.</p>
<p>However, aside from the extra weight of carrying more fuel, the ergonomics of the tank are indistinguishable from the original tank and it allows you to adopt a correct riding position even in aggressive riding. I was quite impressed with this obviously clever design given the massive increase in fuel range. I expect this is because the extra fuel capacity is below the typical fuel tank position.</p>
<p>The (supplied) fittings and mountings for the tank are very strong, particularly for the frame mount, and even after some hard riding (to give you an idea, I wrote off the stock tyre in 15 minutes) there was no sign of fatigue.</p>
<p>After going riding with my mates on a 510 race-style enduro with a 7.2 litre tank, it’s usually me who is the first to complain of the need to return to a fuel supply. Not anymore, not even close. I’m very happy with the purchase of the Safari fuel tank and I would recommend it to anyone. After dealing with some minor fitting issues and the obvious attention given to my complaints, I have no doubt that Safari will have sorted out those issues by now. I would recommend this fuel tank to any fellow enthusiast of Husqvarna high-performance motorcycles.</p>
<p>Some pictures of the bike fitted with the tank follow.</p>
<div class="figure">
<img src="http://i.imgur.com/0eWAR.jpg" alt="Husqvarna TE510 Safari Fuel Tank" />
<p class="caption">Husqvarna TE510 Safari Fuel Tank</p>
</div>
<div class="figure">
<img src="http://i.imgur.com/YFZ09.jpg" alt="Husqvarna TE510 Safari Fuel Tank" />
<p class="caption">Husqvarna TE510 Safari Fuel Tank</p>
</div>
<div class="figure">
<img src="http://i.imgur.com/uJybZ.jpg" alt="Husqvarna TE510 Safari Fuel Tank" />
<p class="caption">Husqvarna TE510 Safari Fuel Tank</p>
</div>
<div class="figure">
<img src="http://i.imgur.com/ns6ZD.jpg" alt="Husqvarna TE510 Safari Fuel Tank" />
<p class="caption">Husqvarna TE510 Safari Fuel Tank</p>
</div>
<div class="figure">
<img src="http://i.imgur.com/Qp61g.jpg" alt="Husqvarna TE510 Safari Fuel Tank" />
<p class="caption">Husqvarna TE510 Safari Fuel Tank</p>
</div>
<div class="figure">
<img src="http://i.imgur.com/WSDmo.jpg" alt="Husqvarna TE510 Safari Fuel Tank" />
<p class="caption">Husqvarna TE510 Safari Fuel Tank</p>
</div>]]></summary>
</entry>

</feed>
